good evening welcome to the Hingham
Board of Selectmen meeting for Tuesday
evening February 13 2008 een first item
on the agenda is the approval of the
minutes from the board's February 6th
session move to approve the minutes of
February 6 2018 second any further
discussion all those in favor aye thank
you
public comment on items not on the
agenda okay next up is the audit
committee recommendation hi might want
to come to the table please I'm Mike
Dwyer chair audit committee Mike so Mike
you've you've actually sent the board a
request so perhaps you could just kind
of brief the audience on the nature of
the request and and what the audit
committee is proposing sure thank you
the town's pure audit services in
three-year increments with the potential
to extend four to three year periods so
at the end of a nine year period and
just ran a request for Proposal
published it had some responses and in
the end found two firms that were
noteworthy that were competitive and we
immigrant some interviews and reference
checks and the report in front of you is
a summary of that process and we're
recommending clifton larsen allen
instead of the incumbent and it please
yeah you can just run your eye over the
the top but what we I think we'd say at
a 10,000 foot report level is that you
are not badly served by powers and
Sullivan what
the incumbent is tried and true but we
are concerned about a renewal becoming
tantamount to an 18-year tenure the
second thing is that CLA did
exceptionally well and made a and
positioned extremely well how they blend
their national strength with local
presence one of the things that I know
in my own work some of the other
financial things these Gatsby
promulgations you know just wave after
wave pension open they're thorny and
powers and saltiness is keeping up
perfectly adequate adequately but our
sense was that a national firm with an
equal and strong local presence is a
compelling story one small detail if I
may is that enough summary is that broad
broadly paint the picture sure one small
detail to bear in mind is the back page
overall pricing is almost identical
again I think these folks get the hang
of how to do this work you know I we can
answer any questions about detail score
and if your lives but one thing that is
worth bringing to our rooms attention I
think is that there is a slight variance
in the columns and that may be worth a
little negotiation into now because as I
understand it not all some of these
entities entities will be paying this
from their own funds so what might look
like a minor variation in columnar
values to us could be pretty serious
material to them so this would seem to
us as you know as the next couple of
steps happen it's not a big tune-up
because the overall price is so close
anything else I can lead you through on
scoring or I mean you know they're all
there was only one area where CLA was
advantageous as opposed to highly
evident
and the fragments and snippets of
chapter 30b we get which is the
procurement statute looks like you know
where there was what they called it
marginal difference or qualitative
difference that we were free to
recommend despite you know rating being
in one area I actually had a question I
one of the things you mentioned in the
executive summary is that CLA does some
sort of an information technology review
just just knowing how much that's part
of our world can well you know what what
do they do I don't want to overstate our
knowledge because this was just brief
from an integer and a recommendation but
they do consider it an accordant of the
audit they do budget some hours for it
and the thing that we thought with the
committee all five of us felt that the
when they were asked a broad question
about risk their response was cyber
security and breaches we thought that's
a very timely now parson Sullivan made a
good point about you know key personnel
that's an always a valid business point
but the fact that in their proposal in
their references and in their assessment
at risk they positioned technology and
cyber security struck us as an important
it caught my attention because the town
is now have the option where people can
pay things online so you think of you
think of citizens entering credit card
numbers and and other sort of personal
information and it just it feels like an
obligation that we have to try to make
sure that their data is well protected
thank you for bringing up one of the key
points I was supposed to mention that
that is you know in the executive
summary for just that reason that we
were all struck that you know building
it into the audit and offering it as the
top area of risk
you know good positioning on the part of
their phone Paula Karen did you have any
other questions it was a very detailed
it was really helpful Mike to read
through all the information and it's
clear you went through a rigorous a
rigorous process yeah I just had one
question in terms of consistency of
staff at the local level
you know I feel like that you know if
you have some confidence in the team
that you have in place locally you know
and I know I know you never know how how
and when personnel changes may occur but
I'm just curious as to sort of what your
perception was would they provide a
dedicated team and Thanks powers and
Sullivan at the partner level has been
100% solid and in all the references for
CLA made a comparable point once you get
a partner you have them for as long as
you want then what happens is that the
manager level they tend to have
reasonable tenures two and three years
and as the junior level is where you
know most of them seem to go at least
two or three years but they don't
guarantee it what I was struck west was
the I was impressed with the Newton
comments where the respondent is now the
mayor and had really operated at audit
committee chair level city councilor in
other words report to us with the audit
and her take across the whole thing was
that the junior turnover was not
troubling and that overall it was so
well managed
there's no no head if you will yeah and
some of the other firms some of the
other references mention those kinds of
timeframes but they all talked about the
partner as being literally you know we
swapped them out when we wanted to have
fresh eyes and the managers being
pretty pretty good tenure how cuz that
address I mean not a perfect answer or a
guarantee no right seemed like it seemed
credible and that's what I wanted to
know okay and then lastly from a process
standpoint I just was wondering about
the role that our town accountant sue
Nickerson played in in this if at all
and you know she contributes um and our
committee work is this is rare for us
this RFP normally were co-editors of the
kafir' and associated documents she's a
leading player in that for this RFP
process we put together the RFP you know
we did that we came up with the
questions and the interviews and did all
that I'll be honest with you she would
prefer stay with the incumbents one of
our committee members who is herself a
municipal CPA said to sue Nickerson well
how were you when you had the prior
accounts and she said well I didn't want
to change yeah and you know so we're
balancing the potential impact we were
very pleased with a the commitment in
the interview the partner manager
started to rattle off we figure 10 or 15
percent extra time from us year one
that's reassuring on a 700 our endeavor
and the second thing was that a couple
of the references notably Worcester said
you know we have credit union of this we
have Worcester Redevelopment Authority
but there's still what he said was the
CFO said they go everywhere but they're
out of here in four to six weeks that
that's exactly what we wanted to hear
that's an efficiency so never can wholly
guarantee but some pretty good you know
again credible statements to address
that issue of turnover okay and last
Mike in the columns and maybe I'm just
missing it is the country-club folded
into
this town side audit or is the country
club it is yes what prompted you to do
this that's in our Charter and so Pallas
and Sullivan has been doing the work for
the town harmony is nine years have
there been any problems reported during
that time no although um a few of the
committee members did focus on this
Shrek findings that we put before you
earlier they're not massive they don't
they're not the kind of thing that shake
the foundation but they're a little
worrisome whether how and whether that
should have been detected and when I'm
not sure but it's I'd say they I would
give them at least a B+ and probably an
a-minus overall nothing wrong with their
work efficient town accountant likes
them but we're a little worried about
incumbency and we definitely were
impressed with the idea that for a
similar quote we're folding in some
information technology that powers and
solidus is not really addressing does
that answer the question Paul connect
can i elaborate in any way no I remember
that when you were here when we signed
off on the financial statements you
mentioned that you know per the Charter
that you would be initiating a
procurement process and you know
especially when you think of auditors
and external auditors one of the reasons
that we initiated the audit committee
and things was to really understand that
the size the size and scope of our town
and I I think what what I'm hearing you
say is that we've had a very very
positive relationship with powers in
Sullivan
and that as part of our due diligence
which I think you know it's good thing
for a triple-a bond community to rebid
many of its professional services
contracts even even if you don't have
any issues just to sort of see if there
might be some benefit and benefit in
making the change you know I I'm
impressed with the thoroughness of your
process you laid out the criteria you
evaluated against the criteria so I
would thank you for all the great work
and defer to your recommendation on this
was it unanimous yes it was and what was
interesting if I may say what gives some
credence to the process is we went
around the table twice at a big meeting
and the first time it was not unanimous
but as the topics came up and we
evaluated and literally traded
incumbency against risk management you
know fresh eyes technology an 18 year
tenure we came to the conclusion that
and the other thing I have to say too is
CLA did a better job in the interviews
we didn't document them because unlike
the references the references were
notable I would say because they provide
new information what I would say
happened in the interviews was that
pretty comparable responses but CLA was
much more observant of the time much
more focused to the committee's
questions and we have no choice but to
consider that as part of the evaluation
process check us if they can do it you
know nearly I mean they were precise
within seconds for our 20-minute
presentation and 10 min
QA and powers in Sullivan you could not
go wrong with but in that setting for
instance it took 45 minutes they were
not as tight that you did a couple even
a couple of us even used the word ramble
so you know you put all all the things
it wasn't in it's not again
you would not be poorly served by the
incumbent I'm sure but it became
unanimous that that there's enough value
here to warrant a change and that the
CLA firm has put enough assurance to
smooth that transition that it doesn't
look like it it'll be a I mean I'd still
contract carefully sure sure just to
clarify some of what I think Mike is
telling us is and I've had several
conversations with sue in the last over
the last couple of weeks during this
process Sue's concerns as Mike has
pointed out are you know she's had some
turnover in her office a couple of
positions are down and she's worried
about the ramp up time for a new audit
firm coming in in the middle of that in
the middle of that turnover and what
that will mean for her operation that
said I think what we have to do was way
that against what we're hearing from our
audit committee in terms of the business
case for an audit firm and the reason so
in and it's a little bit right it's
little bit different than the rest of
the world in the auditing world
sometimes incumbency isn't necessarily a
benefit right so fresh eyes I think is
what Mike is telling us our eyes can can
provide a strong business benefit for an
organization during an audit process so
my initial thought was powers and
Sullivan does a great job and they they
know are they know our process and and
they know our people and they and it
works seamlessly but then I started
thinking about it and they know our
process they know our people and it
works seamlessly and sometimes in a lot
of process that's not it's not really
what you're looking for so I think I
think what Mike is trying graciously to
say is that a shake-up isn't a bad thing
and and all things being equal I think
the the the potential disruption in the
in the art and the accountants office
will likely be brief and and we can
overcome that so I would be hard-pressed
to suggest that you you act a counter to
the to the audit committees thorough
process any questions or comments from
the audience so the process now Mary is
if we award this we'd award it to either
one of these vendors and then we they
come back to us with the contract vote
the vote tonight is whether whether or
not to accept the recommendation of the
audit committee which would then trigger
a negotiation quick to some extent so
just to be clear because this was an RFP
process we are somewhat limited by 30 B
in the negotiations if it was an IFB an
invitation for bid process you have more
leeway for negotiating in the contract
stage now that said I think we can move
some of these dollars around perhaps not
necessarily lessening the total value
and I can talk with the CLA about that
if you were to yes that's what I was
earning about yeah okay but someone like
to make a motion I move that we accept
the recommendation of the audit
committee
second that okay any further discussion
all those in favor hi thank you so much
and at least thanks thanks to the rest
of the audit committee really well done
thank you thank you thank you very much
next on the agenda is a forecast update
and tom has you we have copies in our
packet and Thomas also projecting it up
on the wall so those in the audience can
can see what we've got okay so we
recently did a slight update to the what
I like to refer to as the revenue
forecast however there's not a whole lot
of revenue update being done at this
point but there were significant updates
being done on the on the expense side of
the forecast that we wanted to try to
show everyone the picture as it
currently stands so the main difference
if you'll see in the summary page here
is that our surplus slash deficit line
moved from 800,000 at the last update to
2.5 million and there's a number of
factors that go into that which I'll
I'll review here so on the only real
revenue change in the forecast was the
we had an increase in the sewer revenue
anticipated by forty four thousand
dollars but that'll simply be offset by
the expense increase I don't say simply
I don't mean that
that'll be offset by the expense side as
it'll be covered
it'll be offset by ratepayers I just
jump in and tell Paul and Karen that the
the revenue increase was actually
triggered the MWRA
they essentially you know we that we
have been given budget parameters and
they essentially said I think was what
time a 30% increase it was the whole the
whole Internet is really something like
30% so we we had to increase the expense
we had budgeted 15% this went up to 30
so up an additional 15% so the increase
in revenue is to cover that cost so that
this this budget again remains neutral
to the
that's right now we do still have a
couple of potential updates to the
revenue to the revenue side of the
forecast as state aid as the budget
moves through the legislature we may get
some updates there and then local
receipts still could clarify as we move
forward okay on the expense side we have
article for an additional fifty thousand
two hundred dollars on the expense side
for town salaries and wages we decrease
the expenses by forty three thousand
dollars net that's an eighty eight
thousand dollar reduction offset by the
forty by forty four thousand dollar
sewer increase we just explained the
article four is going down by a total of
one hundred and sixty four thousand
dollars that's in reaction to moving and
some anticipated salary costs for a
couple of unions that have settled in
moving them into their budgets and out
of article four so let's see so we have
one last item the inclusion of a current
administration proposed education budget
this reflects one hundred and twenty two
thousand dollars in reductions since the
initial proposal we have a couple of
potential updates to the FY 9 to FY
nineteen that's the group insurance is
still is still pending
and capital outlay recommendation is
also pending okay our next steps we have
a couple of important dates coming up
the 22nd of February is kind of a big
day across the state the GIC will be
announcing its its group insurance rates
we look forward to getting that
information and as we get it on February
26th we will be re issuing a new
forecast and hopefully by then too we
clarified some of the revenue some
potential final revenue numbers and and
some of these final smaller expense side
numbers so also on the 26th the School
Committee will be voting their education
budget recommendation on the 27th here
the Board of Selectmen will be voting
all town budgets
the week of March 5th we're looking at
the Advisory Committee will be voting
all their budgets after they've done all
their review and of course on April 23rd
we have in the annual Town Meeting
questions nope I had an opportunity to
sue Tom on Monday so we had another yep
so um as you know I'm pretty immersed in
this whole forecast budget kind of thing
and in the last week through a lot of
the hearings I've been I've just been
struck by a lot of different things and
obviously a 2.5 million dollar budget
deficit at this stage is a little bit
higher than we thought and as I've been
listening and and you know thinking
about it myself it struck me that a lot
of the people who are involved in those
next steps Tom described whether its
members of the school committee members
the Advisory Committee there are a lot
of people a lot of people who are new
into their role which is terrific but I
know I've said it and I heard dr. Gallo
say it the other night that in some ways
the the budget challenges we have this
year are sort of feeling like 2008 2009
and you know Karen you were on advisory
at the time so you remember it well and
I kind of thought it might be just
helpful perspective as we're all
thinking about this forecast and in
anticipation of some votes to kind of
look at that a little bit so I just
start by saying those who do not learn
from history are doomed to repeat it and
I just really think it's worth taking a
minute to look back at what happened 10
years ago and some of the lessons that
we learned because I think they might
inform decisions that were making if you
think about 2009 people were feeling
personal financial pressure from a town
perspective our new growth slowed down
our local receipts were slowing down
state aid was getting cut and it was at
that time that we had a negative credit
outlook from the rating agencies some
some of those things are happening right
now
you know that the slower than expected
growth we we still have residents who
are experiencing personal financial
pressure our local receipts you know
sometimes a little variable but I wanted
to focus a little bit on on the credit
rating and the reason for that you know
as we've been hearing all these budgets
you know the the School Committee has
stewardship over the school budget
capital outlay has has stewardship over
the capital budget you know Glenn Olson
and the audience has custody of the you
know the the stewardship of the police
budget I view our board as having
stewardship responsibility for not just
the entire budget but also the bond
rating so Tom if you could advance it in
2009 we got a negative outlook we were a
triple-a bond rating and we got a
negative outlook and we were told at the
time that that was that we could remove
it with a couple of things we were told
that as a town we were not making
sufficient and consistent progress to
fund our retiree health care which we
call a peb at the time it was about a 61
million dollar liability and we had set
aside $300,000 and the rating agency
essentially said you're not doing enough
you're not doing enough consistently we
also at times we were doing a couple
things with capital in years when the
budget was tight we'd cut capital we
would balance our budget on the backs of
capital outlay the other thing we were
doing is we were funding a lot of our
capital out of our rainy day fund our
fund balance in fact between 2005 and
2009 about 25% of our capital or about a
half a million dollars was taken out of
fund balance and that leads to the third
piece which was that our rainy day fund
was do it was dwindling and the rating
agency essentially said you you've got
to stop doing that and you've got to
restore your rainy day fund they also
told us that you know they said well
that's what you need to do to get your
rating to go up what could make it go
down don't do those things they also
said the adoption of a structurally
imbalanced budget if we adopted less
conservative assumptions for revenue and
expenditure growth
or if we used a lot of free cash without
replenishment and and by the way I
should mention that that all these
slides I actually took these from a
presentation that was done 10 years ago
didn't touch them so what you're seeing
is what we literally talked about 10
years ago and I was really struck as I
was looking at these slides that some of
these things still hold true today so
what did we do if we think about our
open we have a 30 year funding schedule
and in fact we saw that open review last
November and our open trust balance is
now 12 million dollars and that's a
combination of both contributions and
appreciation we still have a big
liability and we've learned that our our
current funding schedule is is below
where we'd like to be with capital
investments we did two things we said
we've got a financial policy that says
we should invest a certain amount in
capital every year and we've kind of
stuck to that and we've also stopped
paying for capital out of fund balance
and what that's allowed us to do is to
restore our fund balance the other thing
we talked about 10 years ago was
actually budgeting money for fund
balance and I think what we found over
the years is that at the end of the year
when departments have budget turn backs
or there might be a little bit of extra
revenue that comes through that's gone
into our fund balance and so our fund
balance is actually very healthy right
now and we haven't had to necessarily
put a line item against it the other
thing that we did is some you know Karen
you you did this on advisory I did it I
see Craig McKay in the audience I know
the Advisory Committee is working on it
again we also said let's let's adopt a
financial policy let's put some of this
in writing to kind of guide guide us in
terms of where we want to be and just a
couple of highlights that I think we
want to think about as we think about
the forecast in the budget the first one
says that we should be caught and I
these again are snippets from the
confidential policy the town should be
cautious in incorporating long-term
growth
some shion's into the financial forecast
that means we don't want to push the
revenue too hard we got to focus on on
what we think is going to happen not
what we hope is going to happen that we
should fund our long term financial
obligations and liabilities at a minimum
as required by law and we're doing that
we're doing that with our o peb and then
the last piece talks about when our
unassigned fund balance or you know in
layman's terms when our when we hit our
rainy day target what should we do with
that surplus money and in 2015 the
Advisory Committee said well you should
think about maybe paying off unfunded
liabilities or maybe capital or maybe
debt but I put in read something that I
think again as important as we think
about the budget and the the magnitude
of the deficit that we have excess
unassigned fund balance should not be
used to fund recurring operating budget
items we're gonna get ourselves into the
trap we were in ten years ago if we
start using our rainy day fund to fund
too much of our everyday business and
again I I thought that was instructive
just for the benefit of people watching
you know we're talking a lot about our
bond rating and what's that what that's
worth and again ten years ago we
highlighted that when the town borrowed
for some school renovations our triple-a
bond rating saved us about four hundred
thousand dollars in 2008 when we were
building east school when all the credit
markets were frozen we were actually
able to borrow and we borrowed at a one
just over a 1% interest rate for a
couple of years which allowed basically
you know that that was less dollars that
we had to collect from taxpayers and in
2009 when we issued 43 million dollars
of debt we saved about a million dollars
I talked to Jean Montgomery today and
she mentioned a couple of things that
again our triple-a bond rating have
helped us with recently in 2015 when we
financed the middle school and the high
school field improvement
project we had an interest rate of 3%
and you know how many of our mortgages
are at 3% and then last year we had we
had 20 to 22 million dollar note a lot
of that was for the outstanding balance
on the Lincoln school apartments we were
able to refinance it at one point three
nine percent which saves us two million
dollars over the 13 years remaining on
that bond and again as we think about
the Lincoln school apartments this is
less of a debt service payment they have
to make which means more of the money
can work within the Lincoln school
apartments so that's a little bit of a
benefit um I'll just close so well what
were the lessons learned and what what
might I ask us to think about the next
couple of weeks let's be careful we
don't push the revenue forecast too far
you know sometimes you can look at a
little and an individual line item and
say well a hundred thousand dollars more
we really do kind of have to rely on the
data this next piece I took from a
presentation but it said we need to
forecast and budget expenses based on
available revenue and if we think about
it the available revenue is the ceiling
we got to keep funding our long-term
liabilities we can't be short-sighted on
capital every year our financial policy
says we should spend between I think
it's 2 and 5 percent of our budget on
capital we've we've got a placeholder in
there of about 2.3 million we know every
year that we have capital needs that are
around 2.3 million dollars so as we're
making choices we should keep that in
mind and then lastly keeping the rainy
day fund really for a rainy day not
relying too much on fund balance or
one-time money to balance the budget
because it may not necessarily be there
next year and I think that's
particularly important because many of
the budget initiatives that are under
consideration right now are personnel
related I think before we hire personnel
we need to have assurance that we will
have the ability
to pay that salary not just next year
but the year after and the year after
and we also need to be mindful that as
we look at costs in our budget the
personnel costs tend to be the the
fastest growing budget items and so
again you know I think back to 2009 and
you know Karen you you were on the
Advisory Committee and some tough times
there aspects of right now that sort of
feel a little bit like that and I my
hope is that even if we weren't engaged
in that process we can learn some of the
lessons from 2009 and you know rely on
the processes and policies that we have
in place to guide us as we close out the
budget for this year questions comments
I wasn't on the Advisory Committee but I
was working feverishly to maintain the
viability of the shipyard during that
period so I can well appreciate the
comments that you're making and I thank
you for bringing that to the attention
of the public because we're gonna be
taking some tough votes shortly so
nobody should really be surprised you
know as usual Mary really thorough
I think instructive I think the thing I
would say to sort of follow up on what
Paul's sentiments echo is that you know
over the course of the last 10 years
we've also layered on additional
national and state mandates to all
departments
you know I as I very fond of saying
participated in the Citizens Police
Academy last fall and and heard a number
of additional trainings and priorities
that the police department alone has got
to find within an existing budget you
know I think we heard from the schools
last week about again additional
services that are just you know asked of
you without any dollars coming from or
any meaningful dollars coming from the
state or federal government
- in order to provide those services so
you know again maybe no different than
where we were in 2009 but just sort of
additional layers of you know I think
regulation and and mandates and you know
you you brought a personnel cost you
know when when dot showed her budget
last week about and you looked at the
pie and you saw that giant piece that
was personnel you know that's not unlike
what we deal with on the town side you
know that's how we that's how we run
your local government is with all of the
people that provide services to this
town and those costs have escalated over
time you know not in an unwarranted
fashion or not in an irresponsible
fashion but in a manner that's
consistent with the service levels that
we expect from our town so I'd agree
with you Paul
you know this is not going to be an easy
budget process because I guess what I
want to say is the of the budgets were
reviewing people are asking I think for
the resources they need to try to do
their jobs at the level that that they
see as required of them and what we have
to say unfortunately on our side is you
know I get that and if I were sitting in
your seat I would be asking for those
very same dollars but we have to balance
all of this including as you suggest
overall financial policy and really
financial ongoing financial health of
this town and you know what it meant
years ago and what it may mean today is
some votes where you know people aren't
going to get everything they want I'm
gonna be abstaining most of the time
really well thank you any questions or
comments from the audience okay Tom if I
may ask because when when we do these
forecast updates and things are if we
can put it on the website put both
documents as well to forward to our
colleagues on the Advisory Committee and
the school committee they get the very
detailed forecast
let's also make sure that that they have
everything
okay so we have warrant articles now on
the agenda time I I see that Article V
is listed first but I don't see Bill in
the room should we go ahead with okay
why don't we go ahead with article T if
we could please and maybe you could just
introduce that so last year looks like
it was back in August of 16 the Board of
Selectmen was Nagoya had negotiated with
broad stone bare coal commonly known as
multi known as Alliance who is a forty B
developer down at the end of Beale
Street and the the Board of Selectmen
had negotiated the development agreement
that in among other things
[Music]
culminated in a million dollars for the
town to purchase windows at the Plymouth
River School fifty thousand dollars for
improvements at bear Cove park you know
among other things some sign boards for
the police department etc one of the
outcroppings from that negotiation
included or was also a the deeding over
a parcel of land from their ownership to
the town and I think a lot of people in
town will probably be shocked to learn
that this parcel of land isn't already
the tenants what what what it is it's
the property that at the far end of bear
Cove park that runs right up into the
into the old you'll hang a mutual
building and it's the it's the parcel
land actually that has the I believe the
colored trees on it right so anyway
there's a two point three two point two
three one acre piece of land that's
being deeded to the town as part of part
of the negotiation part of the
development agreement and the
Town Meeting has to vote to to accept
that conveyance so this is actually just
the implementation of something that was
already part of the development
agreement and agreed to by all the
parties that's right okay well our Karen
any questions about this article I
walked the site I'm familiar with it
and Susan signed off she has yes I
remember there were a lot of a lot of
the negotiation had to do with this
particular piece of land so and it's a
development agreement okay with someone
are there any questions from the public
on article T if not could someone make a
motion move to recommend favorable
action on article T second all those in
favor aye Hill welcome we come on up we
are we did we had a legislative update
and we're asked if that was taken off
the agenda Friday I appreciate you
bringing that up because our state
legislators felt that if they came in in
several weeks they would have more
information about the status of the
budget as well as a few other matters so
thank you sir welcome Paul they have a
diagram so this is article VIII which
are the funds for town wars and we have
committee that's an incredible picture
bill good evening to the segment in to
those who may be looking home at us from
home um thank you I you so you have not
prior to my hasty arrival here thank you
for having me this evening catching my
breath as I came up the stairs in a race
the parking lot is full I don't know
what else is happening here tonight
you're empty I don't know we're always
busy here in Hingham bill
so I bring only one physical thing which
is this incredible photo taken on
January 30th this year and this is from
the the ramp leading to the bridge
across to Whitney Wharf and it shows
rather dramatically what sea level rise
and a storm and a high tide can do and
it's pretty damn dramatic is there any
way that can be also put up so I came
before your committee in December and
also with the Advisory Committee in
December to give a sense of where
Harvard development has been and the
place that we landed in terms of a
recommendation to our well really to you
first but ultimately to our consultants
in terms of what the target height for
the for town owned words that we are
considering here and that was ten point
seven feet or give or take and I told
you at the time that in the inst in the
interests of continuing to move this
along that yes I would be back with a
warrant article and while away in
January I did craft a short article and
attach to it and I don't know whether
you received it as well a you know I
suggested comment just to give context
here if you did not or perhaps for the
benefit of the home audience I could
just you know very briefly it's very
simple sure so the article reads will
the town raise an appropriate bar and
appropriate borrow or transfer from
available funds the sum of money for the
purpose of initial repair and
restoration of for town on wharves at
town fear the PIO wmia Park the form of
mobile station parcel and about Barnes
Wharf or act on anything related thereto
inserted it
that our suggestion and the comment and
I'm not jumping ahead of the Advisory
Committee I was just trying to give them
a little context and anybody who saw
this little context of what what is it
that we're doing now you remember we
have money and we are continuing to
proceed with borings initial designs and
ultimately permanent or all four of the
town warps we did that by virtue of
articles passed in both 19 and 2015 and
again last year and so we have funding
already for that and we're beginning to
get just have received some initial
concepts which the harbour development
committee will be considering but we're
looking ahead to when we have those
concepts and we have permits how do we
get started and the notion behind this
article is as follows
article 31 of the 2015 annual Town
Meeting appropriated 175,000 for phase
one of the repair and restoration of the
town world warps focusing first on an
engineering assessment of the condition
of all the wars during 2016 and 17 the
Harbor Development Committee continued
to pursue Phase two engineering design
and permitting using an additional two
hundred forty thousand a probe but
approved by the 2017 annual town meeting
for all four Taliban wars that work will
continue in 2018 with the target of
completed designs and plans and
substantial progress on permit requests
prior to the next funding cycle
application of the Seaport bond Council
on August 2018 seaport bond council
typically entertains municipal grant
requests for funding up to 1 million
dollars annually contingent on matching
town funding equal to 20 percent of the
requested amount the Seaport bond
council is one example of potential
grant opportunities that may require
matching funds the purpose of this
article is to appropriate $200,000
constituting the town's match to begin
what is expected to be continued town
investment in the reconstruction of
these town wars to address their spore
structural condition expected sea level
rise and overall coastal resiliency I
went on to speak a little bit to funding
but I think that's something we should
we should really discuss but having
returned from some holiday away the the
very next day the storm hit and there
were photos this this is a remarkable
photo and I've shared other photos I did
at the December meeting but frankly this
is the highest dive I've ever seen it
and it's a pretty telling
I had an another photo that was from the
the driveway heading down to town pier
and you look out and you know all you
see is water so the the thrust here is
it seems to make sense that we Harvard
Development Committee has always been
try to plan long term but be
opportunistic if this if there's a
chance to go after some funding we
should do that we could structure an
article such that it was contingent on
receiving the grant you know the not the
dollars not be spent on our end because
frankly even a million dollars is not
going to be large in terms of the total
cost of all four of these wharves but it
could potentially be one of the wharfs
I'm not I'm not sure until we have these
concepts decide on a design and then
have our engineers press that out we're
not going to know the numbers but this
is intended to get us started so that's
the that's the thrust and I'd be happy
to respond to any questions and Bill do
we know with with the Seaport bond
council it's up to a million dollars a
year but are they are they in a position
where you know if we're awarded the
grant in one year we can reapply in
subsequent years against the same
project do we know that I believe
there's precedent for that Mary but I'm
I'm not certain yeah and and you know I
other thing I should be very clear on I
mean this is like school grants or any
other grant I mean there are many who
are after this kind of money whether
Hingham would be blessed we know that's
the town the bond council did give us
seven hundred thousand dollars toward
our project at the bait bathhouse snack
shack and they have kind of told us well
we don't want to see you back until we
see see that you've succeeded and I
think that's you know entirely
appropriate though the expectation and
hope would be that by august of 2018 we
would be well on our way to be able to
demonstrate yep here it is you know the
project is proceeding they if you file
in August of eighteen that's for
consideration I think the funding cycle
is six months after that so you know
it's it's time but I if you're denied
one time there's certainly no difficulty
you know in applying again and to my
knowledge they other towns they they
have funded multiple cuts at the same at
the same project and and this is all in
the context you remember one of our
earlier legislative updates Paul I think
you were here Karen I know you were not
but when Garrett and Bob were here they
said they they you know told us and this
is three years ago
look assess the whole thing plan the
whole thing permit the whole thing and
then go after the money but the
opportunistic and it may be you know
piece by piece that's what we're trying
to do that's not to say that this town
may not themselves need to step up and
make this a priority and I was pleased
to see and I want to thank this Luckman
for including in your goals acting on
the recommendations of Town Meeting over
the last several years of prioritizing
moving forward on items at the Harbor
with town
we're being you know one of the one of
the primary items questions bill are you
making any headway on what the design of
the walls is likely to be I mentioned
Paul literally on Saturday I got seven
concepts forwarded from Roger coming
from Beals and Thomas Roger and myself
the vice chair of our committee are
going to meet next week with bills and
Thomas we will up take that topic up at
our next meeting which i think is March
7th this is pretty much on the on the
timeline that we would have expected and
there are some very interesting notions
that are have big begun to be floated we
need to test those and things like you
you don't necessarily have to we've
we've agreed that ten point seven feet
should be our you know across the entire
Harbor does that all have to be right at
the wall front or could it be a two-step
process
where for Barnes Wharf or even through
town pier the front of the wharf and in
the granite wall surrounding it comes up
two plus feet and further back in the in
the in the land you have another
tasteful a additional wall so if you're
willing to allow periodically some water
to go on the floor you know there's
nothing inherently valuable on town pier
the Iron Horse is safe he's up about ten
feet Barnes Wharf might be a different
question once they actually had so these
are things we need to think about
explore with our consultants talk to
Lincoln Marikina Maritime about to you
know see what's going to work for them
because we have our commitment under the
lease so the answer Paul is interesting
notions work to be done
that'd be nice if that could be
televised that meeting yes let me have
our sessions early on with next week to
figure out whether we're ready for punto
i I want to have have it be far enough
along I mean as I said literally last
Saturday the very first notions of what
these concepts might look at the place I
absolutely agree to me
we've talked from the outset that's this
is the marriage of safety cost and
aesthetics and and as a Harvard
Development Committee we've worked very
hard for all of our stuff at making sure
that for the key meetings when we're
really focusing in on this and come to
terms that we did that you know you know
you know meeting that others could see
whether that evening or on a delayed
basis okay thank you so in terms of the
boring design and permitting though in
that that phase one money it sounds like
it is the boring complete on all wharfs
and you're now in in design phase we are
the I know the boring is complete on
barns and temp here I I'm not sure
whether in my absence in the late
December early January time frame they
also did the borings on P o WM IA and
the mobile station okay but the fact
that I'm seeing preliminary you know
concepts or that suggests to me that
they have okay but I more homework to be
done care okay and then the the process
for that would be you would come up with
the design and then you come back here
how does that I've you this as a as
we've said from the outset of a very
kind of interactive thing I mean I think
we need to our committee needs to do its
homework and its diligence and be ready
to come forward with either you know a
single proposal or as we did as I came
to you with the heights you know saying
well look we could do this or we could
do something you know that seems more
and we came to a conclusion and
you you supported that I I expect that
this is not a decision that will be made
in a vacuum and it needs to be inclusive
of a lot of parties here and in town as
you know already there are a number of
other constituencies here who need to be
heard from whether it's the king a
maritime the Historical Commission
historic districts Commission because
several of these parcels and historic
districts so it's got to be lots of
visibility okay and do you have a sense
do you have a sense of an overall number
so you're sort of taking 20% of some no
we're let me be real clear this is is
simply grabbing for what is not possible
okay
the very early on two three years ago
when we sort of asked our consultant
well you know just linear feet for
granite
you know reconstruction you know order
of magnitude and it was a big number
it's it's ten to fifteen million dollars
probably but until we get to a concept
now that we know our conditions know you
know we've we've done this analytical
survey we know where the weaknesses are
if a wall needs to be rebuilt because
remember we're doing two things you know
one we're fixing we're repairing the
existing wall and two we're addressing
sea level rise by thinking about raising
whether at the wall at the pier head or
slightly back in some combination right
raising to this uniform height of ten
point seven feet across these four wars
so I Karen it to be to be fair we're not
going to really have a good number until
we get a concept that we can all agree
on and ask for that to be priced out
okay and so when I sort of come back to
the construct of the question or the
article for Town Meeting and I throw
this out to you and to to Craig or to
the Advisory Committee more generally
and I'm not familiar with this or I
don't know but
this the way the question is worded now
the expenditure the funds would be under
the direction of the Harvard Development
Committee without any input maybe back
to us and then the purpose is for
initial repair and restoration so I
guess I'm a little unclear I hear you
that this could be staged out and there
may be things that we need to do to
repair and restore what we have but
would any of this money also be used for
the increase in the height and I guess
my my question would be do we feel like
that's included in this language of
initial repair and restoration I tried
to be deliberately generic knowing that
I characterize this almost as a down
payment and if if we came back that one
of the worse we could proceed on you
know and make some real you know real
progress on that particular Wharf that
might make sense
so I guess my my response to that is I'm
not sure this language gets you there
and so if we're trying to be as broad as
we possibly could be to allow you know
the greatest flexibility and as you
suggest if we're opportunistic and we
got money and we could we saw our way
clear to be able to complete a project
on a wharf
I guess I'd feel more comfortable if
this language or the ultimate
recommended motion would build in not
only initial repair and restoration but
potential you know potential improvement
I guess might be the language you're
addressing the sea level rise portion of
it because it is both it is clearly both
yeah that's correct and I've been
talking with liaisons actually Craig Dan
Coughlin uh who is also secretary to the
Advisory Committee and therefore
couldn't be here this evening but I
spoke with him yesterday I spoke with
Lucy over the weekend both as to what
this is and secondly and most
importantly you know from a funding
where do we look to for funding sources
and that's something I think we'd like
to get into for a few minutes here but
you know the the thrust is look this is
and attempt to begin going for money
whether it's from from other sources
it's too early to be thinking about you
know ourselves until we've got a better
sense of what the what the final numbers
are going to be so so I think what I'm
hearing Karin say is whether you know
does the scope of the article as it's
written contemplate all these different
possibilities and I think we can't
broaden the recommended motion from the
article so it may also be a place and
you know maybe you know bill you could
fellow at the time if this is a place
where we just need an opinion from
counsel to make sure that all of these
different possible potential uses of
funds are covered in the language that
might you know that that might be a
pricey adjective was initially and I
perhaps didn't focus as much on to me
repair restoration and resiliency have
been part of that from the beginning but
I I just I understand it yeah you may be
right I just want to make sure that
personally I'd like to see the
recommended motion the language in the
recommended motion be as broad as it
possibly could be to allow for the
expenditure of the funds as you suggest
once we once we have a design and we
potentially have funding sources and we
are ready to move money around for these
wharfs you know what's the best way to
spend the money at this particular time
you know and again I I guess I throw
this back to you and ultimately to the
Advisory Committee to consider both the
purp the designation of purpose here as
well as the direction of the you know
the party that's directing the
expenditure of the funds and and I am
you know totally ambivalent in terms of
you know whether ultimately it comes to
the slugman because you would ultimately
sign any contracts I'm not that's that's
not a
I have no concern there and and we are
meeting Craig I think the Advisory
Committee is taking this up Thursday to
hear it on Thursday and to vote sometime
sometime next week so I will continue
those conversations and I hear you I did
want to just spend a couple minutes of
time maybe just on the the source of
funds you know we we get all these
warrant articles and I remember once an
advisor is sort of how are we gonna pay
for all these things and so I think one
of the things we try to do without
necessarily binding the Advisory
Committee is to offer a point of view
and I think you've got a little
preliminary information but we are it
was my intention that we would probably
hear this tonight but not voted until
later date because we would just want to
make sure there's alignment on the
source of funding okay
so there's a couple of options for
funding right we could use the general
fund or we could use mooring related or
Harbor related revenue so the harbor
related revenue you have waterways
account you have a dredging account you
have the mooring fees and speaking
recently with the harbor master and the
town accountant
it appears that within the within a year
to two years we're going to have to have
a dredging project happen in our Harbor
it's a little bit early we haven't done
the sounding study yet but the
anticipation is that within on the
outside two years we're going to we're
going to be dredging the anticipated
cost of this is a very early estimate I
don't have any concrete information
backing this estimate but it's early
estimate from Ken Corson is about 1.7
million dollars for the dredging project
right now we have and again early
estimates no concrete data but as we
look at these different accounts we have
approximately a million dollars
available now
we anticipate in talking to sue
Nickerson being able to fund the 1.7
through those accounts in or close to it
in 2020 so that gives us another year to
try to build those revenues as opposed
to trying to do it this year now the
question is we have the dredging need
and we have the potential the harbor
resiliency project so if we were to seek
an alternate source of funds for the
harbor resiliency project of the
seawalls then that would be a source
that would be probably logically looked
at and the question becomes can we
afford it out of that money and still do
our dredging project the bill and I met
very briefly I talked on the phone very
briefly about this last week I met with
or earlier this week I met with with sue
Nickerson and Ken Corson about this
again earlier this week or late last
week and it's all very preliminary I
hope to be able to put a little bit more
meat on this bone prior to add coms
review on Thursday so this is what I
have for you now and you know I would I
would suggest that you like you had
suggested there that maybe not consider
voting tonight allow me to get some more
information and hopefully answer a lot
of what I anticipate going to be your
questions along the lines of funding
sources prior to your vote could I
supplement a few shares that Thomas
because we did speak yeah three days ago
I think about two things to really
emphasize first the million seven I
haven't been able to catch up to Ken
this weekend or so I
had that conversation but I know you
know he's probably gone to the outside
he really won't know until he does this
are sounding because this it's all
volume it's it's how many cubic yards of
material need to be dredged and he'll
know that once that work is done and we
have money for that there was a grant
actually to accomplish that and we can
do that fairly quickly yes spring so
that that's one item you know the the
second is in terms of the sources this
is something I had looked at hard with
sue in December sue and Ken and and
there are these you know these multiple
sources and maybe one out there we've
talked about and I you know I think it
may be a little higher than what what
tom has suggested and you know what but
but he's right if we chart target at
2020 it sounds like we'd be real close
to the million seven if it is that much
and and as you remember this is the
first time that it's really probably
going to all be on the tight in the past
we've had the opportunities to get get
money from the state the other
opportunity that I know you and Ken and
I have talked about is it may be
possible if we team up with some other
towns to get some volume discounts if
Lima thand Hall and Quincy all needed
dredging you got the dredging company to
mobilize once for all four of those
towns
maybe the million seven number comes
down but I mean I think the you know the
issue remains do we want to be careful
cautious try to preserve the the mooring
permit you know fees and we know that
builds that are roughly 250 260 thousand
dollars a year that's that's pretty well
known so these these are just some of
the parameters do you want to mention
the the
possibility in terms of good well I Tom
and I on in talking you know he posed to
me the question he said build you know I
had drafted my comment initially to say
probably the source is more impairment
fees because that clearly is is relevant
but he asked me the question are you do
you have any particular leaning where it
comes from and and my answer to that was
no I simply wanted to make it as easy on
the rest of the town's budgeting process
as possible knowing that there are
always demands on the general fund and
so forth and I'm assuming this year is
no exception
so his question to me was will look
ultimately are we going to be doing a
pretty big project here and likely to
have to go ahead and bond that we're not
the likelihood of getting all of this
from some theory state god parent is not
high so if you know his question to me
was if we're going to bond this anyway
you know one other issue might be to
borrow the funds and that could be as we
have in the past borrowing from
ourselves packaging it with some other
you know small borrowings knowing that
when we get further down the road we're
going to be we're gonna be bonding
probably a bigger project and sometimes
I think when we've done that in the past
if if that is the long-term financing
plan sometimes the initial money upfront
we've often just taken that out of fund
balance and then when we wrap it into
the borrowing we essentially then
replenish that balance it so there you
know there's some different some
different things here I think we're all
mindful of we want to be careful that we
don't mentally commit the same dollars
to different places I'm also aware that
we have capital outlay coming in and
sometimes the Harbormaster capital
requests get funded from there so I
think we just we we want to look at it
I'll look at all of it in totality
mindful wheat we talked about the
operating budget if you look at the
five-year forecast I think we'd like to
avoid a circumstance where we have to
budget dredging in the article six
budget
so but you know if if if we can make
some headway on this and again I think
we we offer a point of view but
ultimately it is the advisory committees
decision as to the source of funds I
think the information that that we're
going to be getting will benefit will
benefit their recommendation as well
meeting yeah I I had a quite similar
picture at last year's Town Meeting but
this is probably a foot higher than the
one that I showed a year ago and it's
Lucy Hancock I think we actually went
down a red-eye roasters and you know
came away saying when do we start you
know when do we start facing the walls
because it's it's it was pretty dramatic
dramatic bill thank you so much thank
you for deferring your your
consideration of article VIII until like
about this deal Tom why don't we go to
article s next I'm just like we're sort
of we're sort of down near the harbor
okay and article s has to do with a
little bit down by the harbor so we are
as part of our lease agreement with King
a maritime we that we signed last two
December's ago we had the town had
committed to exploring sewer connection
possibilities for that potential is
there for the potential upgrades to that
to that operation and to that end we
have put together or quote looks like
it's in the amount of fifty three
thousand three hundred dollars to to
seek approval from the MWRA
in the form of an engineering
application to both connect bar the
Barnes Wharf site as well as the Hingham
Public Library quite simply because it
was the nearest town facility to the
MWRA s jurisdiction or
boundaries and you know you never know
down the line what you might want to do
in terms of septic vs sewer and if there
was a connection opportunity there maybe
that would be the the least costly of
all of the town buildings that aren't
already on sewer to get them onto sewer
so we incorporated the hang of Public
Library sight the the building or the
location I should say the property into
this quote and again fifty five thousand
three hundred dollars for consulting to
for a consultant to submit an
application to the MWRA to determine
whether or not those sites would be
allowed to be added into the MWRA
district yes you have any sense as to
the what the if such a line is allowed
whether the MWRA
allows other owners to tie in I don't
have a I don't have the answer to that
question I could get a football curious
to know I would imagine not just because
the application process is going to
speak to the flow the anticipated flow
in inflow into their network and if you
were adding additional properties then
that would obviously affect that that
number so I would imagine not and if we
apply or we are we bound to move forward
with no connections thank you I should
have said that in my introduction
absolutely not
these are funds that would be authorized
by Town Meeting to be spent by the town
to to seek these these approvals from
the MWRA it not requires I just had two
things one is that when we you know sign
the lease with hang a maritime we as
part of that lease essentially said that
that the TAT one of the town's
responsibilities and this is a phase one
milestone is that we would try to secure
the approvals because this is this is
necessary to get to get sewer service
and restrooms down on
to barnesworth we also thought that
there would be some economies of scale
with the library and you know in
speaking with the trustees in the
library director while right now the
library doesn't contemplate needing it
it just feels like a good idea for a
little bit extra money to kind of get
that and so we had some correspondence
from David McKean and some feedback from
Linda Harper both saying that if if the
library could be included in the scope
of this it would be helpful do we have
some sense of that incremental
additional cost by including the library
it was yeah it was minimal I want to say
it was an additional maybe ten fifteen
thousand dollars I had the original
quote without that in there from last
year but I don't remember offhand with
that number what that figure was okay
and I think according to the warrant
article language this you know I think
for fifty thousand dollars this is the
kind of thing that we usually take out
of that we usually fund out of out of
fund balance you know and there's you
know in the article six forecasts
there's a look I mean we bring it in you
know I I really like the idea of moving
ahead on this because it it helps us
advance what we want to do with Burns
Wharf and obviously the ability to move
forward on that facility etc and I think
this is also a visible sign not just to
our partners that hang a maritime but
also to the public who will be asking to
contribute to their fundraising effort
this is an important milestone that I
think might just help with some of the
fundraising because it it helps make it
look it's making it real yep I don't
disagree I guess I just heard
conflicting interest on the part of the
library for inclusion in the process and
you know while I understand
incrementally it's ten or fifteen
thousand dollars giving you earlier
slide presentation yep I just
no I if they're saying they want to be
included that's great but my
understanding was they have a working
septic and at this point didn't really
see a need to be tied in so yeah that
was the initial conversation and then
subsequent to that both David Megan and
Linda Harper reached out and said you
know we've we've talked about this a
little bit they ran it by some of the
other trustees and I think the
collective feeling was that it would it
would be helpful okay any questions from
the public would someone like to make a
motion move to recommend favorable
reaction on article 5 Michael s yes
second any further discussion all those
in favor aye
okay thank you the next one is article n
which is to accept Mass General law
chapter 64 and section 3a marijuana
sales tax
Tom do you want to introduce this yeah I
don't have an unfortunately ma so this
is to to allow the town should it not be
banned this is would allow the town to
tax the sales of recreational marijuana
and at the rate of 3% you know I know
we're gonna take up we're going to take
up on that on March 6 we're gonna take
up the question of the general bylaw I
know the Planning Board is working on
the time manner in place regulations
they will also have a zoning bylaw the
reason that we're hearing this now is to
me in some ways this is sort of a
distinct issue and you know it would
seem to me that if if town meeting what
wants to allow these establishments if
they were to operate there would be town
services required to ensure that to
ensure that they were abiding by
regulations and so it it seems to me
that we would want to adopt a favorable
action on article and understanding that
if if a ban is in place that you know
that's a good point and it's 3% of total
sale price received okay which is the
maximum allowed best that's the maximum
allowed yep and you know we try to check
to see you know you know remember when
we were looking to adopt the meals tax
there were estimates that were put out
there but those were actually based on
collections at the state level that this
is a whole new thing so really any sort
of estimates about sales about about
potential revenue you know it feels
really speculative you know more than
zero and and if we don't vote to accept
check to chapter 64 and and the band the
band fails we end up with marijuana
establishments in town when we get no
local tax dollars result correct and
then again you know there will I think
with these establishments there will be
extra extra
effort required extra demand on town
services you think so chief the 3% goes
into the general fund Eddie
any further comment or some like to make
a motion
I vote I do I vote I move to recommend
favorable action on our article and the
acceptance of Mass General law chapter
64 and section 3 marijuana sales tax
sorry all those in favor aye I would
also just point out to the public that
the board voting favorable action on
article and is independent of the
question will be taking up in a couple
weeks which is the question of a ban so
looking forward to that discussion
our final warrant article for the
evening is article you and article you
it you know this is going to be deja vu
all over again last week we had a public
hearing on the naming of a conservation
property located off South Pleasant
Street and so now that we have completed
that we are actually hearing article U
which proposes to give the name Lehner
conservation ant land Lehner
conservation area to the parcels of land
that the town acquired last year with
community preservation funds time we
haven't received any correspondence okay
any questions no all my questions were
answered last time hey I'm gonna make a
motion I move I move favorable action on
article you sir any further discussion
all those in favor aye
okay terrific that takes care that
concludes the warrant articles for this
evening next Tuesday will be taking up
more warrant articles the next item on
the agenda is a Hingham housing
authority 100 Beale Street discussion
Karen I'm gonna
kind of turn this over to you okay
you might recall a couple weeks ago I
updated you and Paul on my work with the
housing authority with respect to a
hundred Beale Street
it's a parcel that in 2001 the Housing
Authority agreed to transfer my 8 acres
8.1 acres something like that to the
town as consideration under contract for
the demolition of ancillary buildings
that were part of the bear Cove Park
baracoa Park site you may recall that we
where we talked last time that we
thought we'd give the Housing Authority
some additional time to kind of think
through the action they took which was
to vote not to transfer that parcel back
to the town notwithstanding a clear
obligation under the 2001 contract so
we're back tonight to to talk about this
some more in the meantime we received a
letter from mr. keys Bob keys who is now
the new chair of the Housing Authority
board in the wake of the resignation of
Dave lien Cooper who was the former
chair of the Housing Authority board and
mr. keys is requesting some additional
time to consider
I guess consider issues with respect to
the parcel you know I I I am a little
frustrated by this I have to say you
know I probably came out a little bit
last week that I'm a little frustrated
to be dealing with this I I started
talking with the housing authority about
the conveyance of the land
last summer I spent some time with
tabeling Cooper with mr. Mayo and mr.
Alexei Attis reviewing all of the files
that we had with respect to the
obligation of the housing authority
under the contract to transfer the
property of the town answered her
questions provided her with
documentation she went back and talked
with her board and I I took a look at
the housing authority minutes and they
were definitely a couple of they meet
once a month and there were definitely a
couple of minutes that reflect
discussions by the board and information
provided to the board by Dave lien of
this contract for this very clear
contractual obligation and you know
notwithstanding I think that length of
time and the provision of significant
amount of information you know to me the
housing authority is still not keeping
the promise that it made to the town I
think last time around I mentioned that
the housing authority did what I would
have done which was request the
diligence package that we put together
demonstrating that the town had provided
or had had provided its consideration
under the contract namely the demolition
of the buildings and it was kind of a
you know dire I cross your teeth have a
request and we pulled together a pretty
thick packet of stuff that includes old
invoices old contracts the contract
itself correspondence maps again
demonstrating that the town kept its
promise you know and I said this last
time around - it's just it's frustrating
and it's also really uncomfortable to be
to be in this situation where an entity
that resides in your town where folks
that you know are residents that you
shop with and go to church with live at
the Housing Authority property on taxer
Street that their governing body is
refusing to keep a promise that they
they made to the town when you analyze
this that parcel is complicated those
parcels over there are complicated there
are restrictions that have been placed
on those parcels by the Department of
the Interior there were restrictions
placed on the parcel by former boards of
Selectmen you know there are wetlands
issues conservation issues
but that has nothing to do with the very
narrow question that's before the
Housing Authority board and that is you
know did you promise in 2001 that you
would transfer this land for the town
Dave Eiland Cooper's a lawyer actually
in affordable housing she's reviewed
that contract and she concluded indeed
the housing authority had a legal
obligation has a legal obligation to
make the transfer they worked with a pro
bono attorney prior to you know prior to
our our last meeting
who my understanding is also concluded
that they had a legal responsibility to
transfer the land to the town
we have spent legal resources with Susan
Murphy not only in analyzing and pulling
together all of the diligence materials
that we've provided to the Housing
Authority but Susan came with me in
November to a housing authority meeting
where we explained all of these same
issues we laid out all of this same
paperwork and we opened ourselves up to
whatever questions
the housing authority had with respect
to the contracts and aside from wanting
the diligence package there were no
questions about the contract itself so I
apologize for being long-winded but
taxpayer dollars
Hingham taxpayer dollars were spent to
demolish the buildings on Housing
Authority property and even though the
Housing Authority like I said before is
sort of like our cousin it is actually a
separate entity it's a separate parcel
it's not the town and so the town
actually can't can't take taxpayer money
and spend it for some other third party
and it can't spend that money for the
Housing Authority without without
getting that consideration back and so
we have an obligation which I think we
talked about before we have an
obligation uncomfortable or not to
enforce this contract
mr. keys has asked for some additional
time I think to consider these issues
and to again consult with counsel and
you know given the nature of the request
you know I and if you concur I would say
that you know he's asking for 30 days
that would put us on or about our
meeting on March 13th and I guess from
my perspective the Housing Authority
ought to be able by before March 13th
come to an understanding of their
obligations under the contract and vote
to convey the parcel back to the town so
I guess if you are amenable I would
suggest that perhaps we take up you know
any further response to the housing
authority on March 13th
ladies and gentlemen I like having these
kind of conversations they were awkward
I served with our mulatto
I know bought keys I know Jim Watson I
know that Jim and Bob signed this
agreement years ago to convey the land
over we paid a quarter of a million
dollars taxpayer doe it's time to pony
up if you need 30 days to come to the
conclusion that you'd agreed to do 10
plus years ago so be it but deal's a
deal
holding you to it and I'm dead serious
about that yeah I would I would go along
with my colleagues I think the three of
us have a responsibility as stewards of
the town we talked about our stewardship
responsibilities earlier in the meeting
when we were looking at the financials
and this this to me is is part of that
role and part of the obligation that we
have as the people that are occupying
these seats right now if I look at the
memorandum of agreement it's very clear
in consideration of the demolition and
removal of the buildings the authority
agrees that it will transfer to the town
of Hingham the parcel of land off Beale
Street shown as live 2 on the plan
attached here to as Exhibit A
so Tom why don't we put this on our
agenda for March 13th and I hope that at
that time we will have a representative
here from the Housing Authority and that
we can bring this matter to conclusion
so that all of us can continue on with
the important that work that we do for
the town
okay any appointments tonight don't
believe so so okay selectmen and town
administrator reports Tom do you have
anything
I just wanted to notify and let everyone
know that I'm gonna read a brief
statement but this is this is a
wonderful program pink patch project is
an initiative of the National Police
movement to support breast cancer
research
the Hingham Police Department was one of
the first departments in Massachusetts
participate in this program on Friday
February 9th chief Olson and
representatives of the Hingham Police
Department went to Boston to deliver a
check in the amount of $2,300 to the
Dana Farber Cancer Institute these are
funds raised by the our HPD in support
of this mission every year and I just
wanted to say congratulations and great
job to you and to your and to your force
and I have a great picture of the chief
with Wally the Green Monster maybe
before we go to town administrator
reports and thank you the when they were
these votes down at the bottom I tend to
something else overlooked them but we
have we have a request to approve a
request of legal seafoods so can you
just sure there's that two gentlemen
that are being added to the legal
seafoods board of directors and as a
result all of their liquor licenses
across the state have to reflect those
names it look like it was consistent
with state law
sure I'll entertain a motion to approve
the application of legal seafoods LLC
d/b/a legal c96 derby street for a
change of manages to the board of
manages as outlined in the letter from
massachusetts alcoholic beverages
control commission dated January 17 2008
teams second
in favor all right okay
Turner Paul I mean any update selectmen
updates ladies and gentlemen Summer
Street corridor pilot program continues
to evolve I want to thank the police and
fire for their robust participation as
well as the DPW we anticipate liaison
with the towns of hall and Cohasset
shortly set out in greater detail what
we're proposing to do the state is
enthusiastic participant and we
anticipate getting quite a bit of data
to support the eventual redesign
I also want to thank mr. Conroy I
thought he gave a great speech on
Lincoln Day and in fact he quoted one of
my favorite lines in Abraham Lincoln
where when he visited Richmond shortly
after the fall of the Confederacy was
asked by his generals whether he wanted
to impose a harsh peace and his words
were let him up easy so I think we're
doing that with the housing authority
[Laughter]
let's let's hope we're right now.just
Lincoln Day to use a Paul Healy ISM was
a great take it's always to me a thrill
to be in that building and it just
really is a special day in hang em
stories I was proud to participate as a
member the board segment yeah it was a
wonderful day and I also appreciated
being back at the Heritage Museum for
the for a little gathering after you
know just before we move into executive
session I just want to acknowledge that
over on the you know the the room next
to us is where Karen's and my former
colleagues the members of the Advisory
Committee are meeting and this is really
they're very very busy time of year
they're trying to settle budgets here
Warren articles they're meeting twice a
week and members are going to other
other meetings on alternate nights this
is just really crunch time for them and
the the quality of the warrant that you
receive and the quality of the financial
and and warrant article recommendations
just reflects a lot of very hard work
from 15 of our fellow citizen volunteers
and just just want to acknowledge and
thank them for the great work that that
they do I know we all have been
interacting with different members of
the advisory committee as we've been you
know going through warrants and budget
and we appreciate all their time so one
and one may be ones one further thing
would be it really represents the
culmination of a lot of committee work
over that time so you know that the
committee's that that like Bill Reardon
here tonight although those folks have
to do their work in advance of this
process and then you know then it hits
this more centralized review and so it's
just really a heavy-lift by a number of
volunteers and the town wouldn't be run
the way it is run without all of that
work and their hearings are open to the
public and they welcome from the public
with that our next meeting will be next
Tuesday February 20th we understand that
that is school vacation week but also in
trying to make sure that we conclude our
business so that our advisory colleagues
can work we do we do have a full agenda
for next week we've tried to schedule
warrant articles that we think are of
great public interest we've we're not
doing those next week we're trying to
also take care of some other other
business before this board so that on
the 27th we will take up budgets and
some other articles we will be hearing
the capital outlay recommendations next
week we will not be
on those we will hear those next week so
with that the board is going to convene
an executive session under Massachusetts
General law chapter 30 a section 21 a to
to conduct a strategy session in
preparation for negotiations with
non-union personnel interim Town
Administrator Thomas Mayo regarding
potential contract and appointment as
Town Administrator the board will not
resume in open session roll call vote
aye aye thank you everybody good night
all right thank you